A Guide to the Stephen Osborne Southall Papers, 1885-1943
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Stephen Osborne Southall Papers, 1885-1943
Library of Virginia
25585
3.30 cubic feet (9 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Valentine W. Southall, Amelia, Virginia, 13 September 1962.
Biographical/Historical Information
Stephen Osborne Southall was born in Woodstock, Virginia on 15 May 1858. He attended Kenmore High School, Amherst Court House, and the University of Virginia. In 1890, he graduated from the Theological School of the Episcopal Church and was placed in charge of the churches in Tazewell County. He also served in Lunenburg Parish in Richmond County, Rocky Mount, Virginia, and Wilmer Parish in Prince Edward County. He married (1) Nelly E. Southall in 1891 and (2) Julia Pride (Wood) on 26 April 1899. The children from his second marriage included three sons: Stephen Osborne, Valentine Wood, and Robert Goode. He died in Amelia County on 10 December 1943.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1885-1943, of Stephen Osborne Southall primarily consisting of genealogical research material for the Southall and related families. Includes correspondence, genealogical notes, pedigrees, horse pedigrees, abstracts of county and church records, and thirty-seven notebooks.
The correspondence includes letters to and from various people either asking for or providing genealogical information. The notebooks (labeled Volumes I-XXXVII) contain genealogical notes, and transcripts of county, church, and census records, correspondence, bible records, and excerpts from newspapers and other publications. This collection includes genealogical information on the following families: Allen, Alexander, Anderson, Archer, Argall, Atkinson, Barrett, Bibb, Bland, Boisseau, Booker, Bowden, Boyd, Branch, Brown, Burwell, Cabanis, Carter, Chappell, Clay, Cobbs, Cocke, Cox, Craddock, Cutler, Cutts, Dabney, Dangerfield, Darricote, Dickie, Dickson, Dixon, Epes, Farrar, Filmer, Fitzgerald, Flournoy, Ford, Fowles, Frost, Goode, Goodwyn, Green, Greenway, Hardaway, Hardyway, Harris, Harrison, Hatcher, Henry, Irving, Jarratt, Jeter, Johnston, Jones, Ligon, Lockett, Macon, Marston, McCullock, Meriwether, Milton, Morris, Moseley, Mutter, Nicholas, Osborne, Platt, Pleasants, Pollard, Pride, Proctor, Pryor, Radford, Royall, Saunders, Seay, Scott, Shelton, Southall, Steger, Stern, Stras, Strass, Sullivan, Syme, Tanner, Taylor, Thaxton, Townes, Underwood, Vandewall, Van Zandt, Walthall, Watkins, Webster, Wills, Wilson, Winston, Withers, Wood, and Woodson.
Note
This collection was transferred from the Genealogical Notes Collection to the Personal Papers Collection.
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1886-1908 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1901-1919 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1930-1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence - fragments, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Green family (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Tanner family (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Wood family (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Wood - Pride - Anderson - Booker families (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Notes on Various Families (Box 1, Folder 15-18)
- Notes on Various Families (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
- Alphabetical List of Marriage Licenses Granted by the Clerk of Chesterfield County Court, 1771-1803 (typescript) (Box 2, Folder 5)
- List of Tithables, Amelia County, 1786 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Volume I, "Scott, Southall, Green, Clay, Lockett, Ligon, Branch, Argall, Epes, Osborne, Tanner, and Hatcher" - This volume contains genealogical notes, abstracts of county records, extracts from publications, and transcripts of Bible records relating to the following families: Argall, Branch, Clay, Filmer, Green, Hatcher, Jones, Ligon, Lockett, Milton, Marston, Moseley, Osborne, Scott, Southall, and Tanner. Pages 165-391 are blank. Includes an index. (Box 3)
- Volume II, "Southall, Underwood, Dangerfield" - This volume includes genealogical notes relating to the following families: Dangerfield, Goode, Macon, Mutter, Southall, and Vandewall. Pages 79-97 and 99- 347 are blank. Also, a number of pages appear to have been torn out. (Box 3)
- Volume III, Contains a history of the Southall family in England, transcripts of letters from Southalls in England regarding the family history, and notes on the family of Dasey Southall. Also includes: biographical sketches of James Cocke Southall, Robert Goode Southall, Stephen Osborne Southall (1816-1884), Dr. Turner Harrison Southall, and Valentine Wood Southall (1793-1861); Bible records for the Cutts family, the Goode family, and the family of Dr. Philip Turner Southall; and transcripts of newspaper articles on various Southalls. (Box 3)
- Volume IV, "Southall, Tanner, Branch, Scott, Osborne, Lockett, Henry, Wood" - This volume contains genealogical notes on the following families: Branch, Brown, Harris, Lockett, Osborne, Saunders, Scott (of Amherst, Bedford, Campbell, Caroline, and Prince Edward Counties), Southall, and Wood (of Goochland County). Also includes information on the English ancestors of the Southall family, and transcripts of testimonials published in various newspapers to Stephen O. Southall on his untimely death. Includes a table of contents. (Box 4)
- Volume V, "Governors of Virginia 1604-1788, Burgesses, General Assembly, Speakers, Clerks of Assembly and Burgesses, Parishes, Division of the State, Settlements, Committees and other officers and facts, and Trustees from 1660 to 1800, Amelia County, Other data" - This volume lists the governors, members of the House of Burgesses, General Assembly, and Council of Virginia, Speakers of the House of Burgesses, Clerks of Assembly and House of Burgesses, Virginia signers of the Declaration of Independence and Articles of the Confederation, some persons to whom charter of treasurer was given, commissioners of court. Also includes information on the evolution of the military in Virginia, information on the creation of counties, parishes, and settlements, transcripts of Littleton Parish register including baptisms, communicants, confirmations, marriages, and funerals, a genealogical chart for the Meriweather family. Much of the material in this volume was extracted from Henning Statutes. Includes an index. (Box 4)
- Volume VI, "St. Peters New Kent, Diocesan Convention 1854, Bath Parish Dinwiddie, Southalls, Tanners, Scotts, Symes, Cutlers, and others" - This volume contains transcripts of marriages, births, deaths, baptisms and clergy from St. Peters Parish (New Kent County); transcripts of clergy, baptisms, marriages, communicants, funerals, and confirmations from Bath Parish (Dinwiddie County) Register; history, inscriptions from Blandford Church Yard, and vestry minutes from Bristol Parish; transcripts of minutes and reports from the Annual Convention of the Diocese of Virginia, 1854; an extract from the Journal of the Convention of the Protestant Episcopal Church in the Diocese of Virginia (20 May 1846); list of lay delegates to the Diocesan Conventions, 11785-1846; and marriage licenses from Chesterfield County, 1771-1831. Also includes a list of family names descended from Pocahontas and genealogical notes on the following families: Allen, Alexander (Robert Alexander family), Archer, Bland, Boisseau, Branch, Clay, Cutler, Goode, Goodwyn, Greenway, Jarratt (line of Reverend Devereux Jarratt), Scott, Southall (North Carolina line), Syme, Winston, and Withers. (Box 4)
- Volume VII, "Miss Bassett mare, Wood, Southall, Scott, Tanner, Pride - This volume includes horse pedigrees, transcripts and abstracts of Prince George County records, and genealogical notes on the families of Branch, Green, Henry, Jones, Scott, Southall, Syme, Tanner, Walthall, and Wood. (Box 4)
- Volume VIII, "Charles City Southalls and Connections" - Contains accounts, loose newspaper clippings regarding the launching of the S. S. Sallie S. Cotton, published story of the wounding in action of William B. Southall at Chateau-Thierry, a biographical sketch of Richard M. Graves, Bible records for the Nicholas and Harrison families, and genealogical information on the Southall family of Charles City. Pages 61-83, 89- 99, 181-323 are blank. (Box 5)
- Volume IX, Includes genealogical information on the following families: Anderson, Green, Jeter, Lockett, Osborne, Pride, Scott, Southall, Steger, Stern, Tanner, Wood. Page 180 includes a brief biographical sketch of the author. (Box 5)
- Volume X, "Notes from Calendar of State Papers, Henrico Marriages, Notes on Various Families" - This volume contains transcripts of Henrico marriage bonds, an index to female names in the Henrico County marriages, and genealogical notes on the families of Clay, Cox, Frost, Pleasants, Southall, Wilson, Wood, and Woodson. (Box 5)
- Volume XI, "Early settlers of Alabama, Notes on Coxes of Chesterfield, Clay, Negro uprisings, Bibb, Saunders, Harris, Wilson, Minutes of Dinwiddie Co." - This volume contains extracts from James Edmunds Saunders' Early Settlers of Alabama, genealogical notes on the families of Bibb, Clay, Cox, Harris, Ligon, Lockett, Saunders, Scott, Wills, and Wilson, a chronology of African American uprisings extracted from the Virginia Calendar of State Papers, Volume IX, and abstracts of 1789 entries from the Dinwiddie County Minute Book. Pages 50-147 are blank. (Box 5)
- Volume XII, "Short Notes on Pride, Cox, Goode, etc." - This volume contains genealogical notes on the Goode and Cox families, and very short notes on the Pride family. The majority of the pages in this volume are blank. (Box 6)
- Volume XIII, Includes transcripts of Cumberland County marriage bonds (extracted from the William and Mary Quarterly), and genealogical notes on the families of Atkinson, Cabanis, Clay, Cox, Jones, and Southall. The majority of the pages in this volume are blank. (Box 6)
- Volume XIV, "Gov. of Virginia 1607-1849, Judges of Supreme Court (Circuit), Members of House and Senate, etc., List of tithables in Amelia County beginning with year 1741-1768" - This volume contains lists of governors, councils of state, judges of circuit superior courts, congressmen and senators, judges, and members of the General Assembly. Also includes extracts from Landon C. Bell's "The Old Free State," minister's returns, marriages and baptisms from the Douglas Register, lists of tithables in Amelia County (1741-1768) and Nottoway County (1771), Amelia County guardians, orphans, and securities, and genealogical notes for the families of Efford Booker, Seay, Steger, and Townes. Pages 126-141 and 147-193 are blank. (Box 6)
- Volume XV, "Amelia Marriages and other data" - This volume includes Southall family information found in the Order Books, Deed Books, and Will Books at the Amelia County clerk's office, and transcripts of letters giving information about different branches of the Southall family in Mississippi, North Carolina, etc. Also contains marriage bonds (A-M) of Amelia County, extracts from "St. Mark's Parish," by Dr. Slaughter, genealogical notes from the families of Clay, Green, Lockett, and Withers, information on the families of Booker, Davis, Green, Johnson, Lockett, Osborne, and Scott gleaned from Prince Edward County records, information on the Lockett family from the Cumberland County records, and information on the Clay, Lockett, and Watkins families from the Chesterfield County records. (Box 6)
- Volume XVI, Contains genealogical notes on the following families: Archer, Bowden, Branch, Carter, Clay, Cocke, Cox, Cutts, Green, Hatcher, Henry, Jones, Johnston, Lockett, Meriwether, Mutter, Osborne, Pleasants, Pride, Pryor, Royall, Scott, Southall, Steger, Tanner, Taylor, Underwood, Webster, and Wood. Also includes a biography of Charles Cutts and transcripts of resolutions of respect for Judge Robert Goode Southall. Pages 269-416 are blank. Includes an index. (Box 6)
- Volume XVII, "Valentine Southall Latin, Algebra Book, Dinwiddie, Virginia" - This composition book contains lists of names with volume numbers, page numbers and year, and transcripts and abstracts of deeds information relating to the Pride family including. (Box 7)
- Volume XVIII, Contains transcripts and abstracts of deeds and wills relating to the Pride family. Provides volume and page numbers of deed and will books. (Box 7)
- Volume XIX, Includes marriages and court record abstracts relating to the Pride family. The majority of the pages in this volume are blank. (Box 7)
- Volume XX, "Halifax Records" - Primarily contains information on the families of Booker, Clay, Green, Henry, Lockett, Pride, and Thaxton taken from Halifax County marriage bonds (1753-1800), deeds, and wills. Also includes notes from the "History of Halifax," an extract of an article from the Richmond News Leader concerning a tomb in Chase, City, Virginia with genealogical information on the Boyd, Burwell, and Goode families, and abstracts from the 1790 Census of the Clay, Green, Osborne, Pride, and Wood families. (Box 7)
- Volume XXI, This volume contains genealogical notes on the Southall family of Charles City County, Virginia. (Box 7)
- Volume XXII, Includes genealogical notes on the families of Anderson, Clay, Hardyway, Pride, and Webster, transcripts of a list of vouchers began 8 March 1805, abstracts of Methodist Conference minutes, excerpts from the Gazetteer of Virginia, and excerpts from Cumberland County records. Pages 3-12 are missing. Pages 13-17, 21-84, and 94-99 are blank. (Box 7)
- Volume XXIII, "Schools, Jno. Randolph of Roanoke, Saylors Creek, Amelia Names" - This volume includes excerpts of letters from John Randolph of Roanoke to his nephew, transcripts of school advertisements published in newspapers, excerpts from Walter A. Watson's Notes on Southside Virginia regarding Saylor's Creek, land patents of William Cox, and genealogical notes on the Anderson, Booker, Clay, Cobbs, and Meriwether families. (Box 7)
- Volume XXIV, "Mr. Virginius Wrenn's Register of his work in Amelia, etc." - Contains transcripts of church assignments, marriage records (1895-1923), baptisms (1895-1922), confirmations (1895-1915), burials (1895-1915), Raleigh Parish communicants (1898 May 1), Bristol Parish vestry minutes (23 November 1721-15 September 1735), and excerpts from will book and Bristol Parish Processioners Returns. (Box 7)
- Volume XXV, "Notes on Anderson, Wood, Pride, Clay, Booker, Cocke, and Green" - This volumes includes abstracts of order books, deeds and wills from various counties, and family charts relating to the families of Anderson, Archer, Booker, Clay, Cobbs, Cocke, Epes, Fitzgerald, Flournoy, Ford, Green, Irving, Lockett, Marston, Osborne, Pride, Scott, Southall, Sullivan, Tanner, Winston, and Wood. Also includes ancestors of Colonel William Byrd and information on Raines Tavern, Prince Edward County, Virginia. Pages 1-44 are missing. (Box 7)
- Volume XXVI, Contains genealogical on the following families: Cox, Craddock, Cutts, Goode, Harris, Henry, Johnston, Meriwether, McCullock, Pryor, Southall, Strass, Underwood, Winston, and Wood (Goochland County). Loose are clippings regarding Gilbert Stuart's portrait of Richard Cutts. (Box 7)
- Volume XXVII, "Prince Edward Marriages, 1780 to 1800" - An alphabetical list, by husband's name, of Prince Edward County marriage bonds. Includes husband's name, wife's maiden name, date of bond, and minister performing ceremony. (Box 8)
- Volumes XXVIII and XXIX, "Book 1st, Notes from the Order Books of Amelia County" and "Book II, Notes from the Order Books of Amelia County" - These volume contains notes on roads, church records, and court houses as found in Amelia County Order Books, 1735-1769. The last two pages of Book I contain excerpts of Amelia Academy 1856 Catalogue including description of school and names of student and their parents. (Box 8)
- Volume XXX, "Worn out register of Amelia Wills New copy in book no. I" - Contains Amelia County marriage bonds, and register of Amelia County marriages with date and of minister performing the ceremony. Loose are abstracts from Prince Edward County Will Book L containing information on the families of Booker, Lockett, Osborne, and Scott, and genealogical notes on the Anderson, Branch, Green, Scott, and Tanner families. (Box 8)
- Volume XXXI, "Copied in book no. I, Abstracts of Wills, some fugitive data" - Includes genealogical notes on the following families: Anderson (Amelia County), Booker, Branch, Cobbs, Cocke, Jones, Locke, Osborne, Platt, Pride, Tanner, and Webster. Also contains abstracts of Amelia County wills including lists of family members, administrators, witnesses, and date; abstracts of Nottoway County wills; an index to Amelia County wills with book and page numbers, and other descriptive data; and a biographical sketch of William Barrett excerpted from William and Mary Quarterly, Volume VII, p. 202. (Box 8)
- Volume XXXII, This volume contains genealogical notes on the Archer, Booker, Branch, Chappell, Cox, Dickie, Farrar, Goode, Green, Lockett, and Pleasants, and Pryor families; lists of original members of the Society of the Cincinnati, Virginia troops in Continental Line; transcript of petition to Council, 4 June 1776, regarding overseers and military service; marriage bonds of Charles City, Elizabeth City, Middlesex, Surry, Sussex, and York Counties; Chesterfield County deeds relating to the Booker, Branch, Lockett, and Goode families; and birth, baptismal, and death register of St. Peter's Parish (New Kent, King William, King and Queen, and Hanover Counties). (Box 8)
- Volume XXXIII, "Register of Raleigh and Dale Parishes and Genito, Inventory of the Rev. W, Proctor" - This volume contains transcripts from registers for the parishes of Dale, Genito, and Raleigh including funerals, marriages, baptisms, communicants, confirmations, and vestrymen. Also includes Booker family genealogical notes and an inventory (appraisement) of Rev. Wm. Proctor. (Box 8)
- Volume XXXIV, "Hanover Records, St. Paul's, Other data" - This volume contains genealogical notes on the following families: Archer, Dabney, Darricote, Fowles, Morris, Pollard, Radford, Royall, Shelton, Taylor, and Wood. Also includes list of communicants; transcripts of Hanover County record abstracts; transcripts of births, baptisms, church wardens, and ministers from Bristol Parish register; vestry minutes from St. Paul's Parish and St. Peter's Parish; and extracts from the Calendar of State Papers about the Episcopal Church regarding appointment and removal of rectors and petitions. (Box 9)
- Volume XXXV, "Southall and some collaterals, Van Zandts - Page 37" - Includes transcripts of letters from other Southalls containing family information and genealogical notes on the families of Cutts, Dickson (Dixon), Mutter, Shelton, Underwood, Vandewall, and Wood. Pages 133-179 are blank. (Box 9)
- Volume XXXVI, "Book No. I, Amelia Mar. Bonds, Amelia Wills, Booker, Andersons, Prides, Woods, Tanners, and others, Indexed" - This volume is the Book No. I referenced to in Volumes XXX and XXXI. See the descriptions for these volumes for more information. (Box 9)
- Volume XXXVII, "Southall, This book was commenced in 1885 when Mr. Southall was 27 years old. He kept the information as it was given to him but never corrected its errors. He had an idea that his aunt Emily Stras was infallible until he searched the records for himself. Other items are of interest" - This volume lists allied families associated with the Southall Family (copied from the Richmond Standard, 9 October 1880), and includes genealogical notes on the Henry, Southall, Winston, and Wood families. (Box 9)